<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/tags/consul/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Michael Hamrah</author>
    <rights>(C) 2015</rights>
    <updated>2014-11-29 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Running Consul on CoreOS</title>
          <link>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2014/11/running-consul-on-coreos/</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Michael Hamrah</author>
          <guid>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2014/11/running-consul-on-coreos/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m a big fan of &lt;a href=&#34;consul.io&#34;&gt;Consul&lt;/a&gt;, Hashicorp&amp;#8217;s service discovery tool. I&amp;#8217;ve also become a fan of CoreOS, the cluster framework for running docker containers. Even though CoreOS comes with etcd for service discovery I find the feature set of Consul more compelling. And as a programmer I know I can have my cake and eat it too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first take was to modify my &lt;a href=&#34;github.com/mhamrah/ansible-consul&#34;&gt;ansible-consul&lt;/a&gt; fork to run consul natively on CoreOS. Although this could work I find it defeats CoreOS&amp;#8217;s container-first approach with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/coreos/fleet&#34;&gt;fleet&lt;/a&gt;. Jeff Lindsay created &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/progrium/docker-consul&#34;&gt;a consul docker container&lt;/a&gt; which does the job well. I created two fleet service files: one for launching the consul container and another for service discovery. At first the service discovery aspect seemed weird; I tried to pass ip addresses via the &amp;#8211;join parameter or use &lt;code&gt;ExecStartPost&lt;/code&gt; for running the join command. However I took a cue from the CoreOS cluster setup: sometimes you need a third party to get stuff done. In this case we the built in etcd server to manage the join ip address to kickstart the consul cluster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second fleet service file acts as a sidekick:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For every running consul service there&amp;#8217;s a sidekick process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sidekick process writes the current IP to a key only if that key doesn&amp;#8217;t exist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sidekick process uses the value of that key to join the cluster with &lt;code&gt;docker exec&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sidekick process removes the key if the consul service dies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two service files are below, but you should tweak for your needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You only need a 3 or 5 node server cluster. If your CoreOS deployment is large, use some form of restriction for the server nodes. You can do the same for the client nodes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The discovery script could be optimized. It will try and join whatever ip address is listed in the key. This avoids a few split brain scenarios, but needs to be tested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want DNS to work properly you need to set some Docker daemon options. Read the docker-consul README.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
