<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title> </title>
    <link>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/tags/bikebuild/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Michael Hamrah</author>
    <rights>(C) 2015</rights>
    <updated>2010-03-16 00:00:00 &#43;0000 UTC</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>Building a Single Speed: Wheel Building</title>
          <link>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2010/03/building-a-single-speed-wheel-building/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Michael Hamrah</author>
          <guid>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2010/03/building-a-single-speed-wheel-building/</guid>
          <description>

&lt;p&gt;By far the trickiest part of building the single speed bike (and, consequently, the most fun) was building the wheel.  I was a little hesitant to take on wheel assembly, but I couldn&amp;#8217;t cop out and not try to give it a shot.  It turns out, it&amp;#8217;s rather easy and a lot of fun.  Once you get the pattern down lacing the spokes is pretty straightforward, and out of all the parts of bike building this step really connects you to the bike.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_372&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignleft&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i0.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0198.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-372&#34; title=&#34;Wheel building, step one&#34; src=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0198-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;The first round of spokes are in. Luckily, the Rebel Yell was close at hand.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-wheels:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;The Wheels&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wheels are a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.velocityusa.com/default.asp?contentID=583&#34;&gt;Velocity Deep V&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8216;s with Origin-8 branded hubs (they&amp;#8217;re actually made by Formula).  The spokes are DT Champions.  Luckily, I didn&amp;#8217;t have to worry about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bikeschool.com/spokes/&#34;&gt;calculating spoke length&lt;/a&gt; because I ordered everything from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ridebrooklynny.com&#34;&gt;Ride Brooklyn&lt;/a&gt; (a great bike store in Park Slope) and they took care of the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;videos:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a lot of research before I got started.  Books weren&amp;#8217;t that helpful, as you really need to learn by example to mimic what&amp;#8217;s going on as you lace the spokes.  I found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qTb3x5VO69Y&amp;amp;feature=related&#34;&gt;best video on building a 36 hole front wheel from the bike tube&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube. I&amp;#8217;d just skip to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AOI3uBztvHc&#34;&gt;wheel building part two&lt;/a&gt; where the action starts.  &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OYl4NO5m16Q&amp;amp;feature=related&#34;&gt;The bike tube also has two videos on lacing a 32 hole rear wheel&lt;/a&gt;.  It&amp;#8217;s the same lacing pattern, but the video goes into a little more depth when building the wheel.  The three cross pattern (which means a spoke crosses three other spokes between the hub and rim) is the same between front and rear wheels.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_373&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignright&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0201.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-373 &#34; title=&#34;MLH_0201&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0201-300x201.jpg?resize=300%2C201&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;The first set of spokes are in. Notice the spoke next to the valve hole. The second set of spokes should go in to the right of this one, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t straddle the valve hole. Or, you can start one away from the valve hole, and string the second set between the valve hole and the first spoke. The alternate side spoke goes in the flange hole immediately adjacent to the spoke on the opposite side.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend watching both sets.  The approach is a little different in that the 32 hole front wheel has you lace one side first, then the other, while the 36 hole rear wheel has you lace alternate sides (you put in for sets of spokes: the &amp;#8220;innies&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;outies&amp;#8221; on both the left and right flange).  The valve hole ends up being in a different place with the rear wheel video- as the author explains, you want it to be between a parallel set of spokes to make using the valve easier.  With the front wheel video the valve ends up being between a slanted set of spokes (I could have also followed the video incorrectly).  Not a big deal; it&amp;#8217;s just a nuanced difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend following the 36 hole front wheel video- it&amp;#8217;s a little easier to get the hub centered in the flange because you lace alternate sides.  My rims have 32 holes and there really isn&amp;#8217;t any difference in building the wheel.  (A 36 hole wheel has 4 sets of 9 spokes each, while a 32 hole wheel only has 8 spokes per set).&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_374&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignleft&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0202.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-374&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0202&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0202-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;I followed the 32 hole rear wheel video, which laces one side at a time. It proved difficult to lace the 2nd side because the hub wasn&amp;rsquo;t centered.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;getting-started:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;Getting Started&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed the rear wheel video because it was more succinct.  However, I messed up in the process and had to start again.  I laced one side, and the hub was off center- one side was flush with the rim.  This made lacing the second side very difficult, as there wasn&amp;#8217;t a lot of give in the hub.  I also had a hard time figuring out where to start lacing on the second side.  I started with the wrong hole, and the hub got very twisted half way through the second side.  I really had to pull to get the nipples connected.  When it proved extremely difficult, I knew I must be doing something wrong.  &lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re fighting the wheel, stop and restart.  You missed something.&lt;/strong&gt; After starting again, I realized where I went wrong the first time with the second set of spokes on the other side.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_377&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignright&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0229.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-377&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0229&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0229-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Notice how the second set of spikes line up with the valve hole. This will put the valve hole between parallel spokes.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;try-and-try-again:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;Try, and Try Again&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I attempted to build the wheel again, using the front wheel video, the process was a piece of cake.  Every spoke went in without a hitch.  The benefit of alternating sides while lacing is the hub is centered in the rim which makes connecting the spokes to the nipples very easy (although, I could have messed that up too when following the rear wheel video).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only glitch (which was a minor issue) is when I did the first wheel the valve hole didn&amp;#8217;t end up between parallel spots.  I either messed up following the video, or the front wheel video didn&amp;#8217;t make a point to lace the wheel in such a way.  The rear wheel video does explicitly call this out.  As long you don&amp;#8217;t end up with the valve hole in a cross spoke triangle you&amp;#8217;re all set.  Then it will be impossible to fill the tire with air.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_378&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignleft&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/comparison.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-378 &#34; title=&#34;comparison&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/comparison-300x201.jpg?resize=300%2C201&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a nuanced difference, but you want the valve hole between parallel spots.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correcting the error when I did the rear wheel was easy- I just started one hole away from the valve hole, rather than right next to the valve hole.  After I twisted the hub to get the spoke slant to start the second side, I made sure I started the second side next to the valve hole.  This way the two slanted spokes are next to the valve hole, rather than straddling it.  This will put the valve hole between parallel spokes.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_375&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignright&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0211.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-375&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0211&#34; src=&#34;http://i0.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0211-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;The wheel after lacing the second side.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;truing:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;Truing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got all the spokes on the wheel I dropped some wet lube on the nipples and tightened every spoke with a screwdriver until only a couple threads remained.  The front wheel came out pretty straight, but the rear wheel was way off.  It just took a little more work with the spoke wrench to get it center.  I came up with a make shift truing stand with the front fork and some plastic sticky tabs (I needed to use the frame to do the rear wheel, but it&amp;#8217;s the same idea).&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_379&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignleft&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0008.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-379&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0008&#34; src=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0008-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Awesome makeshift truing stand, with helpful plastic sticky tabs used in lieu of calipers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I placed the sticky tabs as close as possible to the frame and spun the wheel (the wheel spun forever- the hubs must be really slick!).  When the frame hit the tab it would make a noise, and I would adjust.  It&amp;#8217;s really hard to see the space shift between the tab and the rim.  The noise thing really helped.  Slow and calculated increments worked best- you really only need a quarter turn.  This approach worked for both the horizontal and vertical trueness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no way of properly checking the dish, so I may need to take a trip to the bike store (dish is making sure the hub is centered on the rim).  I&amp;#8217;m also worried that the spokes are too tight.  I read that you shouldn&amp;#8217;t have a lot of spoke tension- the spokes feel firm but I definitely need a second opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-8217-s-next:9e3d2c3958c1dead2d18ffd299d6579c&#34;&gt;What&amp;#8217;s Next&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m hoping to get the rest of the parts tomorrow to finish this build.  I&amp;#8217;ll have another post to show how it all came together!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Building a Single Speed Bike with a 183rd Street Frame</title>
          <link>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2010/03/building-a-single-speed-bike/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
          <author>Michael Hamrah</author>
          <guid>http://blog.michaelhamrah.com/2010/03/building-a-single-speed-bike/</guid>
          <description>

&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;#8217;re getting ready to gear up for summer, my wife was looking for a new bike.  I wanted to get her something cool and unique, and (selfishly) use the opportunity to indulge myself in a bike building project.  I heard building a bike was a pretty straightforward process, and in a worse case scenario I&amp;#8217;ll just bring the parts to a bike shop and have them finish it up.  We knew we wanted to go with a single speed- a friend has a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trekbikes.com/us/en/bikes/urban/soho/sohos/&#34;&gt;Trek Soho S&lt;/a&gt; which I fell in love with.  A single speed is perfect for jetting around the city- really light and nimble.  The acceleration is surprisingly easy and you hit a nice cruising speed quickly.  I&amp;#8217;m anxiously awaiting to compare this custom build with other commercial bikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-bike:5375a95adfae0af00b50d08588b7f5bf&#34;&gt;The Bike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We headed over to the good folks at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ridebrooklynny.com&#34;&gt;Ride Brooklyn&lt;/a&gt; for a recommendation on what to buy.  It&amp;#8217;s a great bike shop with a really friendly and helpful staff.  My wife wanted something light and we both wanted to keep the cost down.  They had two frames handy for comparison: An Origin-8 track frame and a slightly more expensive &lt;a href=&#34;http://183rdstreet.com&#34;&gt;183rd Street&lt;/a&gt; track frame.  The 183rd Street frame was a lot lighter than the Origin-8 (surprisingly so) and has a nice powder coat paint job in black which gives it a cool matte finish.  The owner built a bike using the same frame, so we figured it was the way to go.  My wife is 5&amp;#8217;4&amp;#8243; and we got the 51cm frame and fork.&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_357&#34; style=&#34;width: 300px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption aligncenter&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0196.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-medium wp-image-357  &#34; title=&#34;Getting Ready for the Bike Build&#34; src=&#34;http://i0.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0196-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Half the parts ready to go. My boss says only in NYC do you build a bike in the kitchen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: left;&#34;&gt;
  We also got a pair of Velocity Deep V rims in lime green with Formula hubs and a purple Origin-8 crank.  Once I saw everything together this bike is definitely getting a nickname: &amp;#8220;The Joker&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Build: Bottom Bracket&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0003.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignleft size-medium wp-image-360&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0003&#34; src=&#34;http://i0.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0003-300x200.jpg?resize=300%2C200&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With parts in hand, it&amp;#8217;s time to get building!  I started with the bottom bracket, which is an Origin-8 cartridge style bracket with a length of 107mm.  It turns out I should have gotten the 103mm, but the 107 will work just fine.  Check the specifications of your crank to find out for sure (I thought it would have to do with the frame, but it&amp;#8217;s sized for the crank).  I followed this &lt;a href=&#34;http://bicycletutor.com/cartridge-bottom-bracket/&#34;&gt;video from Bicycle Tutor&lt;/a&gt; to find out what to do.  It&amp;#8217;s pretty straightforward.  Honestly, the hardest part was figuring out how to get the lock cup off the bottom bracket.  Hint: You just pull it off!  I kept turning it and was afraid to pull too hard.  Turns out, not a big deal.  I borrowed a bottom bracket tool, but didn&amp;#8217;t have a torque wrench to find the right &lt;a href=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0007-Edit.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;alignright size-medium wp-image-361&#34; title=&#34;MLH_0007-Edit&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0007-Edit-300x209.jpg?resize=300%2C209&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;resistance.  Using some polylube 1000 to grease the threads,  I just screwed the bracket until it was pretty tight and checked the turn on the spindle.  Seemed alright.  I couldn&amp;#8217;t get the lock cup flush with the frame on the non drive side, but it turns out this isn&amp;#8217;t a big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-headset:5375a95adfae0af00b50d08588b7f5bf&#34;&gt;The Headset&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 183rd Street frame has a threadless 1 &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;8&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;#8243; headtube.  I picked up a Crane Creek threadless headset, and, funny enough, used their great &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canecreek.com/tech-headsets?view=video&#34;&gt;video on how to install a threadless headset&lt;/a&gt;.  I didn&amp;#8217;t have a threadless headset press, and tried using a 2&amp;#215;4 and a hammer to get the bottom and top cups on.  It didn&amp;#8217;t work.  Lesson learned: &lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t try using a hammer to bang your threadless headset on the frame.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_362&#34; style=&#34;width: 150px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignleft&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0005.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-thumbnail wp-image-362  &#34; title=&#34;MLH_0005&#34; src=&#34;http://i1.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0005-150x150.jpg?resize=150%2C150&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Headset fully pressed on frame, but text is off center&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt; &lt;figure id=&#34;attachment_363&#34; style=&#34;width: 150px;&#34; class=&#34;wp-caption alignright&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0006.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;size-thumbnail wp-image-363 &#34; title=&#34;MLH_0006&#34; src=&#34;http://i2.wp.com/www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/MLH_0006-150x150.jpg?resize=150%2C150&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; data-recalc-dims=&#34;1&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&#34;wp-caption-text&#34;&gt;Fork with crown race installed. You can see the sticky tabs I used to true the wheel.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need the right tool for the job.  I didn&amp;#8217;t want to buy a tool, so I brought the headset and frame back to Ride Brooklyn (I should start a side bet to see how many times I need to go back there!) and they pressed the cups on the frame, and used a crown race setter to put the crown race on the fork.  I did mess up a little bit, because I forgot to center the logo on the cups when I put them on the frame. I already had them half on when I went to the store and didn&amp;#8217;t want to deal with taking them off again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;next-steps:5375a95adfae0af00b50d08588b7f5bf&#34;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lacing and truing the wheel was a fun but tedious process.  I&amp;#8217;ll write about that next as well as putting the other parts together, so check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michaelhamrah.com/blog/tag/bikebuild&#34;&gt;BikeBuild tag&lt;/a&gt; to follow on the progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
